{
  "reference_number": "185",
  "clauses": [
    {
      "question": "1. What process should the Government use to set a new emissions reduction target in legislation?",
      "question_index": 0,
      "answer": "The Government sets a 2050 target in legislation now",
      "answer_index": 0,
      "notes": "Anything other than a legislated target is not in accordance with the scientific consensus"
    },
    {
      "question": "2. If the Government sets a 2050 target now, which is the best target for New Zealand?",
      "question_index": 1,
      "answer": "Net Zero Emissions - Net zero emissions across all greenhouse gases by 2050",
      "answer_index": 1,
      "notes": "Anything other than this target is not in accordance with the scientific consensus"
    },
    {
      "question": "3. How should New Zealand meet its targets?",
      "question_index": 2,
      "answer": "Domestic emissions reductions only (including from new forest planting)",
      "answer_index": 7,
      "notes": "No country will have emissions to spare. The science dictates that all countries need to be emissions free by the second half of the\n century. If carbon units are bought off of foreign countries, policy should be put in place to ensure that the country the permit is\n\n bought from is tracking to meet their climate targets. At this stage there is not a single country in the world even close to this. Buying\n units is at this stage is a mute point. The reductions required by each country are so steep that nobody will have units to sell. We\n\n SHOULD NOT be relying on this. We need to reduce our emissions urgently - that is what the science says"
    },
    {
      "question": "4. Should the Zero Carbon Bill allow the 2050 target to be revised if circumstances change?",
      "question_index": 3,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "Only if credible scientific evidence suggests this should be the case. This would be akin to finding evidence that contradicts the\n consensus that smoking causes cancer. Extremely unlikely"
    },
    {
      "question": "5. The Government proposes that three emissions budgets of five years each (i.e. covering the next 15 years) be in place at any given time. Do you agree with this proposal?",
      "question_index": 15,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "6. Should the Government be able to alter the last emissions budget (i.e. furthest into the future)?",
      "question_index": 4,
      "answer": "No - emissions budgets should not be able to be changed",
      "answer_index": 9,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "7. Should the Government have the ability to review and adjust the second emissions budget within a specific range under exceptional circumstances? See p36 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 5,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "If and only if credible scientific evidence suggests this should be the case. This would be akin to finding evidence that contradicts the\n\nconsensus that smoking causes cancer. Extremely unlikely"
    },
    {
      "question": "8. Do you agree with the considerations we propose that the Government and the Climate Change Commission take into account when advising on and setting budgets? See p44 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 6,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "Broadly speaking yes. However more weight needs to be given to the science. Physics will win over economics. At some stage hard\ndecisions will need to be made. A drop in living standards looks likely if the science is followed. We must follow the science"
    },
    {
      "question": "9. Should the Zero Carbon Bill require Governments to set out plans within a certain timeframe to achieve the emissions budgets?",
      "question_index": 7,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "Absolutely crucial. We must be tracking to timeframes. Severe penalties must be in put in place if we are off target"
    },
    {
      "question": "10. What are the most important issues for the Government to consider in setting plans to meet budgets? For example, who do we need to work with, what else needs to be considered?",
      "question_index": 8,
      "answer": null,
      "answer_index": 5,
      "notes": "Honest communication with media and the wider public. Despite the political spin, a 10% reduction in emissions each year on the\nprevious year is not an opportunity. It will require a drop in living standards for high income earners and most people. There is no way\n\naround this. Business and high income earners need to be educated on this. Airlines (Air NZ) needs to be advised that it's business\nis finished in 31 years (it seems unlikely that the jet engine will be replaced anytime soon). Has this discussion been had?"
    },
    {
      "question": "11. The Government has proposed that the Climate Change Commission advises on and monitors New Zealand's progress towards its goals. Do you agree with these functions? See p42 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 9,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "12. What role do you think the Climate Change Commission should have in relation to the New Zealand Emissions Trading Scheme (NZ ETS)?",
      "question_index": 10,
      "answer": "Advising the Government on policy settings in the NZ ETS",
      "answer_index": 6,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "13. The Government has proposed that Climate Change Commissioners need to have a range of essential and desirable expertise. Do you agree with the proposed expertise? See p45 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 11,
      "answer": null,
      "answer_index": 5,
      "notes": "Yes but as per above - the science needs to dictate all outcomes. I would propose that climate scientists have the final say on any\n\ndecisions made"
    },
    {
      "question": "14. Do you think the Zero Carbon Bill should cover adapting to climate change?",
      "question_index": 12,
      "answer": "No",
      "answer_index": 8,
      "notes": "Do not over complicate it or detract from its central goal - reducing emissions"
    },
    {
      "question": "15. The Government has proposed a number of new functions to help us adapt to climate change. Do you agree with the proposed functions? See p47 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 13,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "Yes but again they should not detract from the central goal - to reduce emissions. Adaption should not replace reduction"
    },
    {
      "question": "16. Should we explore setting up a targeted adaptation reporting power that could see some organisations share information on their exposure to climate change risks?",
      "question_index": 14,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "Do you have any other comments you'd like to make?",
      "question_index": 16,
      "answer": null,
      "answer_index": 5,
      "notes": "We have committed would being emissions free by 2050 and I commend the courage to do this (bearing in mind the science shows\nus that this will only leave us with an outside chance of reaching 2 degrees). To be emissions free we are looking at about 10%\n\nreductions per year. Has the magnitude of this task been mapped out in terms of carbon budgets for each individual in New Zealand?\nStarting from next year, people need to be emissions free for 1 month a year; this means no flying, driving or creating emissions from\nfood, power, water, heating. Do people realise this? I think the government needs to be honest with the public, 10% reductions per\n\nyear are probably not compatible with a growing economy This issue is something we have not historically had to deal with on a\nglobal scale. It is unprecedented and therefore requires unprecedented policy making. Government needs to set the course and be\n\nhonest with the public about the situation. We are facing an enormous challenge - greater than any generation in history. Perhaps it is\nprudent for the act to include penalties for politicians and leaders who do not act. Scientist attest to dire consequences if politicians\n\ndo not take drastic steps. This means MAJOR changes as a society in the next decade.\n\n\n\n You have elected to withhold your personal details from publication."
    }
  ]
}
